# James R. Stoup

<u>irstoup@gmail.com</u> | 757.912.0852 | Suffolk, VA 23435

Github: james-stoup | LinkedIn: jrstoup

Secret Security Clearance

#### Profile

Senior developer with 16 years experience in software engineering. Extensive background in backend development to include design, coding, testing, debugging, and CI/CD pipelines. Expertise in modeling & simulation as well as microservice architecture. Very familiar with Agile processes, Scrums, and Sprint management.

## Skills

**Languages** Ruby, Python, Go, Java, C/C++, JavaScript, C#, R, Bash

**Databases** PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Cassandra, SQLite

**Tooling** RMQ, Git, Linux (CentOS/Fedora/Ubuntu), LXC, Jenkins, OpenAPI

# **Professional Experience**

#### Sr. Software Engineer - ACS, Remote (2022 - Present)

Supported the Air Force's development of various modeling and simulation applications to include AFSIM, MSSV, and WebUMC. Work done includes code bases in C++, Java, and TypeScript.

## Sr. Software Engineer - By Light, Remote (2020 - 2022)

Maintained and developed Ruby and Python microservices backed by Postgres and Mongo databases to support a Live-Virtual-Constructive (LVC) cyber range. Focus was on refactoring legacy services, standardizing APIs, and imlementing performance improvements.

### Sr. Software Engineer - InCadence, Newport News, VA (2017 - 2020)

Modernized an Army training simulator by implementing new features in the core Java application. Additionally improved the devops environment by increasing automation, standardizing documentation, and streamlining the customer experience. Improved data integrity of the Postgres database by implementing tools to validate existing data and purge corrupted records.

#### Sr. Software Engineer - Novetta, Remote (2015 - 2017)

Primary developer for a resource management web application for use by Army senior staff. Designed system using Go and ExtJS, created UI mock-ups, handled database architecture, and guided overall system design. Managed testing procedures, documentation, and deployment. Designed a database solution using Cassandra and SqLite.

### Software Engineer - Alion, Norfolk, VA (2012 - 2015)

Developed new capabilities for the military simulator JSAF. Worked on a team responsible for enhancing JSAF's core features and improving stability. Primary work done in C++, to increase the fidelity of sonar model.

**Software Engineer - Quantum - Newport News, Virginia (2009 - 2012)**Developed content for the military simulator Virtual Battlespace 2 (VBS2) to train personnel deployed to active war zones. Based on intelligence briefings, new Al behaviors were created, and the simulation refined to reflect current enemy strategy.

2004

# Education

Christopher Newport University, Newport News, Virginia Bachelor of Science in Computer Engineering with Minor in Applied Physics